<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>GlobaLID</title>
<link>https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>The Global Lead Isotope Database project develops next-generation tools for working with lead isotope data in the archaeological sciences.</description>
<generator>quarto-1.4.550</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>New data online in 2023</title>
  <dc:creator>Thomas Rose</dc:creator>
  <link>https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/posts/20240104_Data2023.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Thanks to the efforts of our <a href="../team.html#regional-editors">regional editors</a> and the <a href="../team.html#core-team">GlobaLID Core Team</a>, the amount of data in the GlobaLID database grew significantly: from 2700 data points at the end of 2022 to more than 4100 data points. Our spatial coverage also increased with data from Sub-Saharan Africa and South America. You can find a full list of countries for which data were added on the News page of the <a href="https://globalid.dmt-lb.de/">web application</a>.</p>
<p>More data is currently reviewed and prepared – stay tuned!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/assets/Blog_Data2023.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Coverage of the GlobaLID database end of 2023.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/posts/20240104_Data2023.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/assets/Blog_Data2023.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="72" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Interactive textbook online</title>
  <dc:creator>Thomas Rose</dc:creator>
  <link>https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/posts/20231215_Textbook.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>For several months now, the GlobaLID Core Team has been working on “Lead Isotopes in Archaeology: An Interactive Textbook”. The aim is to provide an open educational resource about the lead isotope method and its application in archaeology as a textbook. In contrast to traditional textbooks, the format as a webpage allows the inclusion of interactive content and other multimedia elements. In addition, it makes it easy to update and expand the textbook over time. The textbook is designed as an edited volume to give appropriate credit to all contributors.</p>
<p>We are delighted to announce the launch of its first version: <a href="https://archmetaldbm.github.io/GlobaLID-Edu/" class="uri">https://archmetaldbm.github.io/GlobaLID-Edu/</a></p>
<p>This initial version was supported through an <a href="https://nfdi4earth.de/2participate/education-training?view=article&amp;id=314&amp;catid=15">NFDI4Earth Educational Pilot</a>.</p>
<p>Admittedly, it is still in the very early stages with only a couple of chapters available but we already wanted to give you an idea about our approach. More chapters will become available in the next months.</p>
<p>We are looking forward to your feedback! And please get in touch if you are interested in contributing or writing a chapter – we are happy to collaborate!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/posts/20231215_Textbook.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/assets/pxhere.com_799419_CCO.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Gathering the lead isotope community</title>
  <dc:creator>Jay Stephens</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Virginie Renson</dc:creator>
  <link>https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/posts/20231102_Workshop.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>When GlobaLID was announced, there was general enthusiasm for a standardized repository of geological lead isotopic data (ourselves included - no more sharing of excel documents!), but it quickly became clear that such a large endeavor would require a community to operate and maintain. One of the crucial points raised in this initial phase of the database was how to design a system of standards that both ensures its applicability to global contexts, while also integrating with the research of scholars who are already successfully applying the method. Because of these nuances, GlobaLID, in partnership with the Deutsches Bergbau Museum Bochum and the Ruhr University of Bochum, invited scholars from all over the world to a conference in Bochum, Germany in February, 2023 in order to discuss their ideas for creating such a database: from the back-end structure, to establishing standard protocols data evaluation, formatting mechanisms for data submission and tools for interpretation, educational materials, and overall goals of the project.</p>
<p>Beyond the usual introductions and reconnections, day 1 of the conference was focused on the research of conference participants in order to better understand the variety of ways in which current projects interact with lead isotopic data and databases. These talks seeded an already fertile soil for discussions on how users would interact with the GlobaLID database, how we would approach the issue of standardization, and integrate with the legacy of database creation for archaeologists applying lead isotopic analysis.</p>
<p>With the stage set, day 2 of the conference was divided into thematic presentations, focusing on the structure of the database, how to create a standardized platform, and the metadata which should be included. Important to this discussion was an overview of other, already existing, regional databases. GlobaLID’s vision is to create a link which would bind these databases together, integrating the nuance of regional specificity with the broad applicability and reach that a global database affords. Another seminal part of the discussion surrounded the issue of credit and how to ensure that researchers submitting data to GlobaLID would receive recognition for their efforts (and citations in future studies!). As a possible solution to this issue, Kirsten Elger gave an overview of data journals, which can host previously unpublished lead isotopic data with a report of the methods with which they were collected. Publication in these data journals allows the data to be fully citable and will generate a DOI. This ensures that any researcher submitting unpublished data would receive two benefits: 1) a publication that they could list on their CV, and 2) citations of this publication for any study making use of their data. Day 2 also included presentations from Patrick Degryse, Tzilla Eshel, Naama Yahalom-Mack, and Daniel Finn, who collectively summarized the statistical and visualization techniques that scholars routinely employ when evaluating the lead isotopic signature for archaeological artifacts. These presentations served both to discuss current approaches for this practice, as well as select methods that researchers would like to see as available tools on the front-end of the GlobaLID platform.</p>
<p>Unlike days 1 and 2, day 3 was structured with multiple sessions operating in parallel, to discuss specific topics of interest to participants and establish the overall framework for GlobaLID in component parts. Thematic focus groups included: metadata, standardization, visualization and statistical tools (<a href="../workshop-archive.html#many-lids-but-none-matching-the-vessel">full programme of the workshop</a>). For these break-out groups, participants outlined important components that should be instituted in each of these thematic topics before re-aggregating for the final discussion. One of the most important developments from these break-out groups was the creation of “regional editors” which are the focus of another <a href="../posts/20230820_RegEd.html">blog post</a>.</p>
<p>We are two of the regional editors for GlobaLID, and for us, this conference was a great opportunity to meet and interact with colleagues applying lead isotopic analysis to various parts of the global archaeological record. It was also an important moment to set a benchmark for where we, as a community, see lead isotopic analysis going in the future. GlobaLID reflects this vision: it is compatible with the present, but forward looking. The team at GlobaLID is currently implementing points raised during this conference, and hopes to run a follow-up conference in 2025.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/posts/20231102_Workshop.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/8/84/Program_Evaluation_%26_Design_June_2013_Workshop_33.jpg/320px-Program_Evaluation_%26_Design_June_2013_Workshop_33.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>GlobaLID gets funded by the DFG</title>
  <dc:creator>Thomas Rose</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Sabine Klein</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Helge Wiethoff</dc:creator>
  <link>https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/posts/20230823_Funding.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>We are excited to announce that GlobaLID received a major grant from the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG; German Research Foundation) for a three-year digital infrastructure project to turn the prototypes into a full version. The project will start in February 2024 and will include many opportunities for you to provide feedback and input to ensure that GlobaLID will meet your needs and expectations. In the major work packages, we will continue to work on</p>
<ul>
<li>An online database that stores lead isotope data in accordance with the FAIR principles, enhanced by workflows for the publication and curation of the data</li>
<li>A metadata scheme to provide sufficient context to the lead isotope data in a well-structured way</li>
<li>A web application to access and work with the database and to carry out common tasks when working with lead isotope data</li>
<li>An interactive textbook as a collection of open educational resources about all aspects of the lead isotope method</li>
<li>Bringing the lead isotope community closer together and providing training through workshops</li>
</ul>
<p>More information will become available in early 2024 – stay tuned!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/posts/20230823_Funding.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/assets/pxhere.com_1058395_CCO.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Regional Editors</title>
  <dc:creator>María Florencia Becerra</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Katrin J. Westner</dc:creator>
  <link>https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/posts/20230820_RegEd.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The <a href="../workshop-archive.html#many-lids-but-none-matching-the-vessel">workshop in February 2023</a> featured insightful and thought-provoking keynotes as well as intense and fruitful discussion rounds, which yielded several stimulating impulses for the future development and further growth of GlobaLID.</p>
<p>One of the prepositions jointly worked out in the discussions was to establish Regional Editors, who will curate the data for specific geographical regions. In practice, they will use their expertise when quality-checking data and metadata from (local) publications concerning the regions they are responsible for, and, with support from contributors, they will add data from their regions to GlobaLID’s database. The Core Team will carry out the final checks of the enriched data before they will become publicly available.</p>
<p>So far, six colleagues already joined the GlobaLID Team as <a href="../team.html#regional-editors">Regional Editors</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Southeast Asia: <a href="https://iramat.cnrs.fr/user/oliver.pryce/">T. O. Pryce</a> <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7290-141X"><img src="https://info.orcid.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/orcid_16x16.png" class="img-fluid"></a> (Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, UMR 7065 Institut de Recherche sur les ArchéoMATériaux, Université Paris-Saclay &amp; CEA/CNRS UMR 3685 NIMBE, 91191 Gif-sur-Yvette, France)</li>
<li>Iran: <a href="https://www.bergbaumuseum.de/en/museum/mitarbeitende/kontakt-detailseite/dr-nima-nezafati">Nima Nezafati</a> <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5806-343X"><img src="https://info.orcid.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/orcid_16x16.png" class="img-fluid"></a> (Forschungsbereich Archäometallurgie, Leibniz-Forschungsmuseum für Georessourcen/Deutsches Bergbau-Museum Bochum, Bochum, Germany)</li>
<li>Africa: <a href="https://archaeometry.missouri.edu/staff.html">Jay Stephens</a> <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1299-3946"><img src="https://info.orcid.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/orcid_16x16.png" class="img-fluid"></a> (School of Anthropology, University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ, USA; Archaeometry Laboratory, Research Reactor Center, University of Missouri, Columbia, MO, USA)</li>
<li>North America:
<ul>
<li><a href="https://archaeometry.missouri.edu/profile(Virginie).html">Virginie Renson</a> <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5701-0985"><img src="https://info.orcid.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/orcid_16x16.png" class="img-fluid"></a> (Archaeometry Laboratory, Research Reactor Center, University of Missouri, Columbia, MO, USA)</li>
<li><a href="https://anthropology.arizona.edu/people/dave-killick">David Killick</a> <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8964-750X"><img src="https://info.orcid.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/orcid_16x16.png" class="img-fluid"></a> (School of Anthropology, University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ, USA)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>South America: <a href="https://www.conicet.gov.ar/new_scp/detalle.php?id=29835">María Florencia Becerra</a> <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6302-7452"><img src="https://info.orcid.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/orcid_16x16.png" class="img-fluid"></a> (Facultad de Filosofía y Letras, Universidad de Buenos Aires, Instituto de Arqueología, CONICET, Buenos Aires, Argentina; Forschungsbereich Archäometallurgie, Leibniz-Forschungsmuseum für Georessourcen/Deutsches Bergbau-Museum Bochum, Bochum, Germany)</li>
</ul>
<p>The first contribution from Jay Stephens on sub-Saharan Africa with 468 entries is already available online. María Florencia Becerra and Virginie Renson currently work on data from Southern and Northern America, respectively, which will successively be added to the publicly accessible revised database.</p>
<p>GlobaLID is a community-driven and peer-curated project. <a href="globalid@bergbaumuseum.de">Get in touch</a> and join <a href="../team.html">the team</a> to contribute to GlobaLID and to help unleashing the power of FAIR data!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/posts/20230820_RegEd.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/assets/globalid-logo.svg" medium="image" type="image/svg+xml"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>GlobaLID at the NADAC summer school in Berkeley, CA (USA)</title>
  <dc:creator>Thomas Rose</dc:creator>
  <link>https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/posts/20230730_NADAC.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Members of the GlobaLID Core Team are participating in the <a href="https://alexandriaarchive.org/nadac/">NEH Institute for Advanced Topics in the Digital Humanities “Networking Archaeological Data and Communities”</a>, a two-year programme of The Alexandria Archive Institute / Open Context. The institute teaches about the management of archaeological data in monthly online workshops and in-person summer schools.</p>
<p>I was able to attend the <a href="https://alexandriaarchive.org/2023/08/23/icing-on-the-cake-lessons-from-the-2023-nadac-summer-workshop/">first summer school</a> in July 2023 at the Badè Museum of Archaeology on the campus of Pacific School of Religion in Berkeley, CA (USA). It was a very welcomed opportunity to meet the other participants in person after seeing them via Zoom and to get to know each other in real life. After short presentations of the current state of the participants’ projects, the summer school programme focused on data management plans and linked data.</p>
<p>In preparation for the summer school, each project drafted a data management plan (if not already existing) which was then discussed in small groups. This allowed us to get deeper insights into some of the projects and especially how data are handled by them. The feedback provided a lot of helpful suggestions for the revision of the data management plan but also for the project itself.</p>
<p>Linked data were only briefly touched upon in one of the online workshops and were now discussed in detail: How do they work? What are the benefits? But also, what are the challenges and risks of linked data? Inspiring presentations by the experts and brainstorming sessions on different aspects of linked data led to a much better understanding, many new ideas for the projects and an annotated collection of resources on this topic.</p>
<p>Although everyone was happily busy working on the topics for the workshop, the programme left enough room to get to know each other, discuss our projects in more depth, and get a better understanding of current debates about the handling and preservation of cultural heritage and data gathered from and about it. A tasting of local wines organised by the staff of the Archaeological Research Facility of the University of California Berkeley, a walking tour of the architecture of North Berkeley’s “Holy Hill” neighbourhood, and a great selection of dinner places allowed getting a good impression of Berkeley and its surroundings.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://alexandriaarchive.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Leigh_NADAC_11-scaled.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The participants of the NADAC summer school in front of the Badè Museum of Archaeology (Photo credit: Alex Roman, used with permission by the NADAC team)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/posts/20230730_NADAC.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://alexandriaarchive.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Leigh_NADAC_11-scaled.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hello, world!</title>
  <dc:creator>Thomas Rose</dc:creator>
  <link>https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/posts/first post.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>GlobaLID is constantly growing but until now there was no single point of access for all resources of GlobaLID. Moreover, the web application as the most important product so far does look nice on small screens and mobile devices. Therefore, this page was set up. Have a look around and explore what GlobaLID already has to offer, what is planned and how you can become part of it.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://archmetaldbm.github.io/globalid/posts/first post.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
